RG 028:005, Governor's Commission on Services and Expenditures (Etherington Commission), 1971
Connecticut State Library
Governor's Commission on Services and Expenditures records
1959-1973
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Governor's Commission on Services and Expenditures
30.5 cubic feet
The Commission studied State government to determine the most efficient and economical means to deliver services to citizens.
RG028_005
1979-040
Historical Note
In his first Executive Order, dated March 17, 1971, Governor Thomas J. Meskill established a Commission to undertake, "a study and analysis of the offices, departments, boards, commission, councils, and other agencies of the State and of the functions of State government to ascertain the means by which and the manner in which the services of the State of Connecticut may be afforded to its citizens in the most efficient, expeditious, and economical manner." Edwin D. Etherington, President of the National Center for Voluntary Action, was appointed Chairman, and the Vice Chairman was Richard M. Stewart, retired Chairman of the Anaconda Brass Company. The work was done, "at no cost to taxpayers" by Commission members and some sixty Study Team staff provided from the management staffs of Connecticut business firms, with other expenses covered by funds raised by four Finance Chairmen from business and private donations. Expert assistance in the study and in administering the work was provided by Warren King and Associates of Chicago, with Thomas D. Evans as Resident Consultant.
Most of the research and investigatory work was done in a period of twelve weeks, April to July, 1971, and the final report, a document of 265 pages, was published in October, 1971
(The Report of the Governor's Commission on Services & Expenditures
, D G747se).
Scope and Content
Includes report drafts, working papers, minutes, correspondence, reference materials, and back-up files.
Arrangement
The file numnbers referred to in the Container List follow this plan:
5. Governor's Office
6. Secretary of the State
7. Treasurer
8. Attorney General
9. Comptroller
10. Tax Department
11. Personnel Department (see also 23, 24)
12. Public Works Department: (see 163 for Office of the Commissioner)
13. Office of Business and Administration
14. Division of Real Assets and Capital Projects
15. Division of Buildings and Grounds
16. Department of Finance and Control:
17. Office of the Commissioner
18. Budget Division
19. Purchasing Division
20. Central Collections Division
21. Office of State Planning
22. Department of Community Affairs
23. Personnel Policy Board (see also 11, 24)
24. Personnel Appeal Board (see also 11, 23)
25. Debt Service
26. Connecticut Development Commission
27. Connecticut Research Commission 28. State Police Department
29. Department of Motor Vehicles
30. Connecitcut Safety Commission
31. Military Department
32. Labor Department
33. Department of Consumer Protection
34. Insurance Department (see also 9, 131, 135)
35. Public Utilities Commission
36. Liquor Control Commission
37. Workmen's Compensation Commission
38. Unemployment Commission
39. Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities
40. Municipal Police Training Council
41. Real Estate Board
42. Miscellaneous regulatory commissions
43. Connecticut marketing Authority
44. Board of Accountancy
45. Industrial Building Commission
46. Civil Air Patrol
47. Department of Agriculture and Natural Resources:
48. Division of Agriculture
49. Division of Parks and Forests
50. Division of Fisheries and Game
51. Division of Water Resources
52. Division of Geological and Natural History Survey
53. Division of Shell Fisheries
54. Boating Commission
55. Agricultural Experiment Station
56. Department of Education:
57. State Board of Education and Services for the Blind
58. Commission for Higher Education
59. Administration ("covered in 58")
60. Central Office, Board for State Colleges
61. State Colleges
62. State Technical Colleges
63. Central Office, Regional Community Colleges
64 Regional Community Colleges (combined with 63)
65. University of Connecticut
66. Health Center, University of Connecitcut (comnbined with 65)
67. State Library (see also 161)
68. Teachers' Retirement Board
69. State Commission on the Arts
70. Historical Commission
71. Student Loan Foundation
72. Commission on Aid to Higher Education
73. Department of Transportation
74. Bureau of Rail and Motor Carrier Services
75. Bureau of Aeronautics
76. Bureau of Waterways
77. Administration
78. Office of Personnel
79. Office of Fiscal Services
80. Office of Staff Services
81. Office of Right of Way
82. Data Processing
83. Bureau of Planning and Research
84. Bureau of Highways
85. Office of Design
86. Office of Traffic
87. Office of Engineering Service
88. Office of Revenue
89. Office of Stores
90. Office of Property Control
91. Office of Administration
92. Office of Construction and Maintenance
93. Division of Tolls
94. Division of Town and Federal Aid
95. Department of Health
96. Central Office and Division of Public Health
97. Office of Public Health
98. Office of Mental Retardation
99. Office of Tuberculosis Control, Hospital Care and Rehabilitation
100. Department of Mental Health
101. Fairfield Hills Hospital
102. Connecticut Valley Hospital
103. Norwich Hospital
104. Undercliff Mental Health Center
105. Alcohol and Drug Dependence Division
106. High Meadows
107. Connecticut Mental Health Center
108. Dubois Treatment Center
109. Security Treatment Center
110. Division of Community Services (combined under 100)
111. Veterans Home and Hospital Commission
112. Department of Welfare
113. Commission on Services for Elderly Persons
114. Soldier's, Sailor's, and Marine's Fund
115. Governor's Committee on Employment of the Handicapped
116. Department of Correction
117. Commissioner's Office
118. Parole Services and Supervision Division
119. State Prison
120. Operations Division
121. Business Administration Division
122. Treatment and Training Division
123. Medical Division
124. State Jails
125. State Farm and Prison for Women
126. Department of Child and Youth Services
127. Long Lane School for Girls
128. Connecitcut School for Boys
129. Board of Pardons
130 Adult Probation Commission
131. Insurance Purchasing and Other Non-Functional Expenditures (see also 9, 34, 135)
132. County Sheriffs
133. Miscellaneous appropriations to the Governor
134. Other Non-Functional expenses
135. Insurance Purchasing Board (see also 9, 34, 131)
136. State Employees' Pension Fund (see also 151)
137. Surety Bonds and Other Insurance
138. Forms and Printing
139. Space and Real Estate (combines with 144)
140. Communications
141. Voice and Data (combines with 140)
142. Mail
143. Messenger (combines eith 142)
144. Property management
145. Banking Department
146. Data Processing
147. Information Systems (Appllications); Computer Operations
148. Personnel
149. Fleets
150. Connecticut mortgage Authority
151. Retirement Division (see also 136)
152. Steamship terminal Commission
153. Connecticut Transportation Authority
154. Connecticut Transportation Authority
155. Ambulance Commission
156. Medical Examining Board
158. Planning Commission on Criminal Administration
159. Henry Whitfield House
160. State Employees' Suggestion Award Board
161. Records Management (see also 67)
162. Division of Concessions (Dept. of Transportation, Bureau of Highways)
163. Office of the COmmissioner (Public Works Department)
164. State Employees' Retirement Commission (see Comptroller)
165. Office of Civil Defense
166. State Traffic Commisson
168. Medico-legal investigations
169. State Bond Commission
Related Material
RG 028:001, Commission to Investigate the Advisability of COnsolidating Certain State Boards and Commission and to Investigate the Public Health Laws, 1915.
RG 028:002, Commission on Reorganization of State Departments, 1935-1937.
RG 028:003, Commission to Study the Integration of the State Judicial System, 1943-1945.
RG 028:004, Commission on State Government Organization, 1949-1950.
RG 028:006, Committee on the Structure of State Government (Filer Committee), 1975-1977.
RG 028:007, Human Servuces Reorganization Commission, 1977-1979.
RG 028:008, Governor's Study Group on Limitation on Expenditures, 1978-1979.
RG 028:009, Commission to Study the Management of State Government (Thomas Commission), 1989-1991.
RG 028:010, Commission to Effect Government Reorganisation (Hull-Harper Commission), 1991-1992.
RG 053 Commission on Civil Administration Code, 1919-1921.
Index Terms
Persons:
Etherington, Edwin D; Steward, Richard M
Organizations:
Connecticut. Governor's Commission on Services and Expenditures
Subjects:
Administrative agencies -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Governor's Commission on Services and Expenditures -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Executive departments -- Connecticut; State governments -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
These records came to the State Archives in Speptember 1978 from the Office of Policy and Management.
Container List
- Records, 1959-1973
  - 1. Report drafts, 1971; 11 binders (no. 2-12, no. 1 is missing) (10 inches)
    Draft of the final report of the Commission, apparently at a stage immedieately preceding printing.
    - No. 2-7 (Box 1)
    - 8-12 (Box 2)
  - 2. Report drafts and "Individual recommendation rerpots", 1971; 1.75 cubic feet
    Reports by team members on their study of particular matters, with recommendations and supporting data, along with early drafts of the final report.
    Arranged numerically according to the filing plan listed in the Arrangement section.
    - Files 5-28 (Box 3)
    - Files 29-69 (Box 4)
    - Files n73-96 (Box 5)
    - Files 130-168, unnumbered (Box 6)
  - 3. Miscellaneous report drafts and working papers, 1971; 1 cubic foot (2 binders + unfiled material) (Box 7)
    Materials similar to those in numbers 1 and 2 above.
    Unarranged.
  - 4. Executive Committee minutes, 1971 April 5-June 17; .5 inches (Box 8)
    Includes agendas and roster of personnel.
  - 5. Correspondence, instructions, etc., 1971-1973; 4.5 inches (Box 8)
    Letters on distrubtion of the final report; material on implementation work following the report; report writing guide; motes and memoranda on the work of the Commission and the consultant staff.
  - 6. Reference materials, 1959-1971; 7 inches (Box 9-10)
    Reports and strudies presumably used as background material. Included are studies of the economic development and competitive position of the State, 1959-1975; strengthening management and budget functions, 1971; consolidated statewide cost allocation plan, 1971; public investment planning, 1970; "choices for Action," 1967; and various Connecticut Public Expenditure COuncil documents.
  - 7. Back-up files and working papers, 1971; 26 cubic feet
    Reports, notes, memoranda, interview reports, corresopndence, draftr reports and recommendations and other materials pertaining to the investigation of the functioning of individual agencies.
    - Files 5-9 (Box 11)
    - Files 10-11 (Box 12)
    - Files 11,12,16 (Box 13)
    - Files 16, 19, 22, 26 (Box 14)
    - Files 27-30 (Box 15)
    - Files 31-33 (Box 16)
    - Files 34-47 (Box 17)
    - Files 48-55 (Box 18)
    - Files 56-66 (Box 19-22)
    - Files 67-73 (Box 23)
    - Files 73-94 (Box 24-32)
    - Files 97-140 (Box 33)
    - Files 144-149 (Box 34)
    - Files 150-169 (Box 35)